<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Iqbal, Rileks La.</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://iqbalabd.me/en/</id><updated>2017-06-15T16:00:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Changing the world one PyCon at a time</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-15T16:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-06-15T16:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2017-06-15:en/changing-the-world-one-pycon-at-a-time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Changing the world one PyCon at a time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an engineer, programming languages are very important tools to solve the
problems that you face. As an entrepreneur, they are also important tools to
bring your imagination to life, to get that profit and making that difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a magnificent programming language. Although first released in 1991, it &lt;em&gt;arguably&lt;/em&gt;
only started to become mainstream&lt;sup id="fnref:fn01"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn01" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; when
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum"&gt;Guido van Rossum&lt;/a&gt;, the creator of
Python joined Google in 2005. That made many people start to notice how serious
the tech giant was investing in Python. In the same year, the web framework
Django which is written in Python was released, and that further pushed Python into the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, even our very much loved
&lt;a href="https://thenewstack.io/instagram-makes-smooth-move-python-3/"&gt;Instagram uses python&lt;/a&gt; 
to handle it's hundreds of millions of requests. Python are also used in
scientific and academic fields&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using Python since 2002, and in many ways it has given me the
intellectual challenge I craved, allowed me the freedom to bring my imagination
to life, and through PyCon, has allowed me to meet wonderful people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My First PyCon, APAC 2010 in Singapore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a programming language is only as good as the people that uses it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_Conference"&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt; is in essence a conference
centered around the Python programming language. It's roots started with the first PyCon in
Washington D.C in 2003 and has expanded to many parts of the world, from Europe, Japan,
China, India, HK, Taiwan, Australia, New Zealand, Singapore and also Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until 2010, before attending my first PyCon, I had been using python for fun
and profit for 8 years. I find the language easy to use, has design that fits
with my mind and how I believe coding should be, and most importantly I enjoyed using
it to build stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I saw the poster for the first PyCon APAC in Singapore in 2010, I
decided to meet the people behind it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC 2010 Singapore" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-apac-2010-poster.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't know anyone there but I'd thought I'll just make new friends and see
what other cool stuff everyone else was building. And made friends I did: I met up with
three other participants from Japan: Manabu Terada
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/terapyon?lang=en"&gt;@terapyon&lt;/a&gt;),
Yasuhi Masuda(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/whosaysni?lang=en"&gt;@whosaysni&lt;/a&gt;) and Ian
Lewis(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ianmlewis?lang=en"&gt;@ianmlewis&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as it turns out, the chairperson for the first PyCon APAC in Singapore was Liew Beng Keat
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bengkeatliew"&gt;@bengkeatliew&lt;/a&gt;) a Malaysian from Kuala
Lumpur. We have more in common than I thought!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bringing PyCon to the region&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was then that Beng Keat was telling me the reason he wanted to organize a
regional version of PyCon APAC: Beng Keat had the opportunity to attend PyCon in
the United States, and although he enjoyed the conference and came back englightened,
he also realized how prohibitive it is to travel from Asia to the United States
and so he thought: &lt;em&gt;If we can't go to PyCon in the US, we'll bring
PyCon here.&lt;/em&gt; And since Singapore was such a small place, it makes more sense to
make it a regional conference instead of just a local conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of having a regional PyCon is in essence a very simple one, with a
well defined purpose: We understand that nearly all of the advances made in
technology by the programming language, new concepts and philosophy in thinking about the
language and even how communities are organized towards a greater good for
everyone at large originate mostly in the United States and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we cannot be in the United States to meet and listen to the great minds that shape
the programming language, its community and its future, lets have those minds
here instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at that first APAC PyCon in Singapore, one of the keynote speakers was &lt;a href="https://github.com/holdenweb"&gt;Steve
Holden&lt;/a&gt;, who was the chairman for PSF&lt;sup id="fnref:fn02"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fn02" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, 
who later on was a pivotal figure for the growth of PyCon within APAC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Building the Japan PyCon community, circa 2011&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We invited Steve to come to Tokyo after APAC, and over dinner we talked about
having an annual conference to get pythonistas from all over the country to come
and share their work and discuss their ideas. Steve was instrumental in proding
us, who had no experience at all running conferences, to actually take the idea
seriously. Given also the fact that Python was still considered an obscure
language in Japan as opposed to PHP, Java or Ruby, we were also sceptical that
there will be any traction at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Steve Holden in Tokyo" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/steve-holden-in-tokyo-02.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dinner with Steve in Roppongi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Steve Holden in Tokyo" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/steve-holden-in-tokyo-01.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;With Masuda-san and Takizawa-san&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following that dinner with Steve, Terada-san, Masuda-san and myself met again on the
1st of July 2010 in an underground Turkish restaurant in Shibuya and over dinner decided
to have our first stab at a PyCon in Japan. We agreed to start small, and host
APAC when we are ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Email calling for the first PyCon meeting" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/shibuya-email.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had our first &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/site/pyconminijp/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;mini&lt;/em&gt; PyCon JP&lt;/a&gt; 
on a cold January morning in 2011 at the Rakuten offices in Tokyo. I was 
involved as the program manager, choosing talks and deciding the contents of the conference.
130 people came for the mini conference, and we all had a great time listening
to talks, learning and making new friends. The conference was free, and everyone
had bento for lunch provided by our generous sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraged by the turnout and how the first conferece went, we then decided to
have a major PyCon JP for the first time in that summer of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyCon JP have been held every year around summer since then, and in 2016 our
attendees topped 700 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to 2012: An issue that we faced after the second PyCon in 2012 was that it was getting
too big, and the left over money from sponsors was getting too much to handle
out from an individual account. We also needed a face for the public, and a
definate entity that will take responsibility for managing the annual conference
in Japan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of that, the non-profit PyCon JP was established in March 2013, which I
am still currently serving as part of the board members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prepare to host APAC, since 2012 we needed to give an international flavour for the
conference, and we made it a point to have at least one track which will be in
English only. This has attracted participation from nearby countries, such as
South Korea and Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To also attract interest from the public, and due to the fact that our
non-profit run on money gained from public interests, we also made it a point to
have an open non-profit general meeting during the local PyCons. It is here
where we met other people which are thinking or are interested in running their
own PyCons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PyCon APAC in Japan, 2013&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singapore had been organizing the APAC conference for 3 years in a row since
2010, and following the model of PyCon US of moving the venue to different cities
every two year, for 2013 they approached us in Japan to take over APAC and organize
it in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been preparing for this since 2011, so we agreed. Our Taiwan counterpart
was also keen on running APAC, but after discussions they agreed to bid for
2014 instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was good for us in the region on 2 accounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The regional conference APAC has finally moved away from Singapore to a
  different city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have another host decided for 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in August 2013, we organized PyCon APAC in Shinjuku, Tokyo, and that is where
we met all the many people that will spread PyCon across the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Asia Pacific Connection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regionally, we have a loosely knit community that drives PyCon APAC
(Asia Pacific). Ideally, PyCon APAC is a regional conference that rotates
between cities within the APAC region, and aims to be an international
and bigger conference giving the opportunity to the regional python
community to come together at a more accessible and affordable location compared to
having to travel to the United States or Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the APAC conference in Tokyo in 2013, there was consensus from the regional
community representatives such as Singapore and South Korea which we managed to
get in touch with when they came to APAC in Tokyo, to move the APAC conference to Taipei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there was no other community which has shown interest to host APAC for
2015, the conference stayed in Taipi until 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC dinner in Taipei" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-apac-tw-06-2015.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;With Van Lindberg, Chairperson for the PSF, Beng Keat, and our friends and staff organizing
PyCon APAC TW in 2015.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The South Korean community, after having their first local PyCon in
2015 stepped up to the plate to host APAC in 2016, and was succesful with over 1000 attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC meeting in Seoul 2016" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/apac-meeting-seoul-2015.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A community meeting of representatives from the different countries in APAC
during the 2016 APAC conference: KR, JP, VN, TW, PH, MY, HK and SG was present&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC meeting in Seoul 2016" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-apac-seoul-2016-group.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Group picture after the community meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regional communities have done a wonderful job to boost their local PyCon
conferences to be a well known annual event to gather and share knowledge among
their Python users. The regional APAC conferences has also proved to be a
platform where new community leaders from neighbouring countries come to connect
and learn how to organize their own local PyCons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make it a point to reach out to fellow community members from countries which up until now
have no representation in our loose group, like Myanmar or Vietnam.  I've seen fellow pythonistas
who came to a PyCon APAC for the first time, and their eyes light up and they smile and say
now they want to start something in their city and their community after
experiencing the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC dinner in Taipei" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/dylan-jay-bangkok.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Meeting up with Dylan Jay in Bangkok. Dylan is the former lead for the Sydney
Python Users Group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collective knowledge of all of us help to remove some anxiety and help guide
them on what are the points that they'll need to keep in mind to start something
for their own city, from organizing know-how to even getting sponsorship
funding. The PSF in this regard have been supportive in providing grants and
also speakers to the APAC conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Connecting pythonistas in Malaysia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After helping out with running PyCon in Japan, I realized that all the PyCons
that we had in the APAC region has all been on the north-eastern part of Asia
Pacific, with the exception of Singapore, but all of them were either cost or time
prohibitive to the rest of Asia Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that begin my next project: To kickstart an annual PyCon in Malaysia grown
for the locals, from the locals, and bring APAC and the rest of the world to Kuala Lumpur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My aim is to have an APAC conference here in Kuala Lumpur as I believe, compared
to the north-east of Asia Pacific, a conference here will be more accessible to
much more people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If we can't go to PyCon, we'll get PyCon here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Malaysia, the history of PyCon started in 2014 where we had our
first mini PyCon (1 day, single track and 70 people attended) and
continued with PyCon MY 2015 (2 days, 2 tracks and around 140 people
attended) and PyCon MY 2016 (2 days, 2 track and around 100 people
attended). I was involved as the co-chair and finance person for the mini
PyCon 2014, the chair for PyCon MY 2015, and co-chair again in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read more on us at &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/"&gt;https://pycon.my/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we start running an international conference like the APAC, we need
to know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to at least run a conference. Having local experienced people to organizing
conferences will also allow us to convince the other regional members that we
are up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014 there was already a loose group of Python users, who had meetups once every
2 or 3 months mainly around the Kuala Lumpur area, usually attended by more or less 10 people.
As is common for any non-profit, grass-roots volunteer driven small meetups with no
monetary or marketing support from commercial entities, these meetups were mostly
attended by the same group of people and before long you'll have organizers burning out,
running out of steam and also things to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The de-facto organizer for these meetups then was Swee Meng, and I met him the first
time at one of Singapore's PyCon. When I suggested to him an annual PyCon for Malaysia,
he was sceptical at first, given his bitter experience with user meetups. He was not convinced
that people will come, but I told him that that is beside the point. If only 10 or
20 people come, so be it. That will be our Malaysian PyCon. Either way it goes,
that will be our learning experience, and we'll see where that leads us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since our first mini PyCon in 2014, many people have helped us, especially the
kind generosity of venue providers, like iTrain, University Malaya and
International University of Malaya-Wales. Nearly all the time we've had help
from the academic staff of the universities who do use Python as a learning tool
and wanted their own students to get involved in academic conferences like
PyCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mini PyCon MY 2014" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/mini-pycon-my-2014.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Our keynote for mini PyCon MY, &lt;a href="http://ericholscher.com/"&gt;Eric Holscher&lt;/a&gt; giving
his talk. Eric was in Kuala Lumpur for vacation and also decided to
contribute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon APAC dinner in Taipei" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-my-um-02-08-2015.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Members of PyCon JP coming in to support our first PyCon MY in University
Malaya&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon MY 2015" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-my-2015-hello.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Kicking off PyCon MY 2015.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon MY 2015" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-my-2015-group.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A group picture at the end of PyCon MY 2015.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon MY 2016" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/pycon/pycon-my-2016-group.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;And the group picture at the end of PyCon MY 2016.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if coming to a full circle, one of the keynote speaker for the first APAC in
Singapore in 2010 (Steve Holden), and another keynote speaker for the first PyCon JP in 2011
(&lt;a href="https://ziade.org/resume.html"&gt;Tarek Ziadé&lt;/a&gt;, who works remotely in the bushes of Dijon, for Mozilla)
was our keynote speakers in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am happy to report that Tarek enjoyed his first ever durian here in Kuala Lumpur when keynoting for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the model that we did in Japan, we have also setup a &lt;a href="https://pycon.my/about/pycon-my-plt/"&gt;partnership&lt;/a&gt;
in Malaysia to facilitate managing funds and also as a public-facing entity to be
responsible for managing PyCon in Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The local sponsors&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our local sponsors who have supported us until now are mostly small companies with
personal relations to one of the member of the staff, that uses Python in their
products or day-to-day operations. These companies are the most generous. They
do not sponsor large amounts, but they are always ready
to give a helping hand. I believe they are the ones who truly understand
and appreciate how difficult it is to organize such a conference, and the value
that it will bring to them and to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our 1st local PyCon we did have big name companies that sponsored us, like
Amazon Web Services (AWS) and &lt;a href="https://www.braintreepayments.com/"&gt;Braintree&lt;/a&gt; a 
subsidiary of PayPal. But the young and still inexperienced Python crowd in Malaysia
might not be a compelling reason yet for them to continue sponsoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PyCon APAC in Kuala Lumpur&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2017, after making a proposal to the APAC community, we have been
selected to hold the responsibility of having PyCon APAC 2017 in Kuala Lumpur,
which will be held in August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I would like to take the opportunity to highlight here is the
wonderful work the community has done to bring PyCon APAC 2017, from
universities, student volunteers, local companies and most of all the
people that make up the community itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally in the Malaysian context, I believe we need more makers or
programmers in our ecosystem. I feel that we focus too much on the
business side of things, with "business focused" conferences like
match-making or raising venture capital. But these are all moot without the
actual people and know-how to build what we want to sell. PyCon MY is
that small ripple we're making to have a positive contribution to the
overall builders and programming ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the title of being a regional conference, we now have the clout to invite
successful technology practicioners from overseas to give talks and share their
insights and ideas with the local crowd. This will hopefully spark interest and motivate
them to further improve their skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Changing the world one PyCon at a time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through PyCon, the community also tries to practice common ground principles
based on universally accepted ideas and ideals. All regional or local PyCons which requests
grants from the PSF &lt;a href="http://pyfound.blogspot.jp/2012/12/psf-moves-to-require-code-of-conduct.html"&gt;are required to have a &lt;em&gt;Code Of Conduct&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that governs how they organizers manage the conference, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; 
also how the attendess behave and interact with one another during the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These Code Of Conducts reflect the values of the community and what they think
is important. Not all talks during PyCons are about programming, web frameworks
or libraries: Some of them are about the experiences of the speaker walking the
path to become a female developer in an industry widely regarded as male dominated,
or the need to have more diversity and how it's achieved through free community
training programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focused groups like PyLadies (python group focused on women),
DjangoCon (Conference focused on the Django framework) and SciPy
(Conference for the users of python in the academics and science
fields) also all contribute to these same ideas and ideals while adding more
spice to the already vibrant python community. In all this PyCon is the general
conference that tries to cover many usages of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the spirit of the community at large and the values and ideals that we
try to have, for APAC this year and for the first time in the history of PyCon in Malaysia,
we are trying a few new things, such as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial Aid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tie up with Women Who Code (WHC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having the conference at a commercial conference venue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reducing waste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subsidized ticketing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Financial Aid, tie up with WHC and subsidized ticketing all aims to increase
participation from under represented groups who could not have attended the
conference due to financial reasons, or also from female tech communities, which
historically have little participation in tech conferences locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in a way, PyCons are not &lt;em&gt;only just&lt;/em&gt; a technical conference that you might
expect from practicioners of a certain technology: It's also sort of a social
movement. Although in PyCons you do have booths for companies the commercial
aspects are very much watered down (as opposed to RISE or Web Summit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the PyCon and it's culture blooming in this part of the world, I
hope it will continue to be a place pythonistas regardless of experience
continue to meet, exchange ideas, interact and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, the aim of a conference like a PyCon, similar to the experience museums
or art galleries offer is to enlighten you and transform you to a different person intellectually
from that person that you were before attending the conference. In the context of
conferences, this is mostly achieved from the human interaction that you've
achieved listening to and discussing about talks and interacting with other attendees.
These transformations does not have to be huge leaps. Knowledge transfers take
time and require us to work on the new information many times in our minds before we can fully
appreciate and understand them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing the world starts here, by us, one good idea at a time and through one PyCon at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn01"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/27207/why-was-pythons-popularity-so-sudden"&gt;Why was Python's popularity so sudden?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn01" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fn02"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/"&gt;Python Software Foundation, a non-profit in the US that holds the
intellectual rights of Python&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fn02" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="pycon"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="apac"></category><category term="community"></category><category term="kuala lumpur"></category></entry><entry><title>Disunity via Schools</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/disunity-in-malaysian-schools.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-28T11:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-05-28T11:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2017-05-28:en/disunity-in-malaysian-schools.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The question of Malaysia's schools not doing its part in fostering unity among
Malaysians have been brought up again due to TN50&lt;sup id="fnref:Ref1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:Ref1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and Business FM did a program to
source opinions from the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I followed the podcast on &lt;a href="http://www.bfm.my/talkback-thursday-unity-in-schools.html"&gt;BFM's TALKBACK THURSDAY: UNITY IN SCHOOLS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an enlightening podcast that puts light on the thoughts and feelings of the
general public on where they think the schooling institution in Malaysia should
head in the context as a tool to promote social unity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Education_in_Malaysia"&gt;Education in Malaysia&lt;/a&gt; for a 
quick primer on the history of schools in Malaysia, or search for &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.jp/search?q=controversy+vernacular+schools+malaysia&amp;amp;oq=controversy+vernacular+schools+malaysia&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57.6788j0j7&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#q=pros+and+cons+of+vernacular+school"&gt;controversy of vernacular schools 
in Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;
for some more background reading. The &lt;a href="http://penanginstitute.org/v3/resources/articles/statistics/714-demographics-of-a-diverse-malaysia"&gt;Penang
Institute&lt;/a&gt;
also has data on the diverse demographics of children attending the different
schools. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Pua"&gt;Tony Pua&lt;/a&gt; also
&lt;a href="http://educationmalaysia.blogspot.jp/2007/03/national-vs-vernacular-schools.html"&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt;
about vernacular schools with insights on how the vernacular school
educationists look at the rhetoric of their schools being the reason of our
disunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The current times questions the difference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By and large the callers basically supported a single-stream school, but many with
caveats, such as pointing to the failures of the so-called national school to be
to be regarded as a symbol of excellence and is part to blame the rise of
so-called vernacular schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Twitter poll by BFM also suggested that the majority who took the poll
supported a single-stream school:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BFM's Poll for Single Stream School" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/bfm-single-stream-school-unity.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have my own thoughts on schools in Malaysia, and it's perceived position as a
tool for national unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why is education a partisan issue?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education for our children, by itself is a subject that we should all be in
agreement. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of us wants the best for our children. We want them to have
good grades, enjoy school life, eat nutritional food at school and grow up a
happy, compasionate, intelligent and balanced child. But this issue now has became a partisan
issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also sure that we all agree that as a nation, a good education for our children is an
important part of building the future of our nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it has became a partisan issue when we take things which are not directly
related to education that aims to develop our children into that balanced human
being, such as racial or religious identity into the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racial or religious identity are exlusive to a particular person or group in the society
and these are the things that puts us apart instead of bringing us together.
When we bring these identities to the public sphere and relate to them it will
of course create exlusitivity and if it's something that not all of us can strive to be (like
race for example) then it will eventually create resentment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is absolutely nothing wrong in being a Dayak who is a Buddhist
or a half-Thai half-Chinese Christian or a Javanese half-Bajau Muslim. All are
Malaysian and all want a better future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of our children what is important is that they know that these people 
exists in our society. They are our neigbours, the people that we see at shops, buy things
from, sell things to. They are the ones which we should help when they ask for
help, and they are also the ones that will help us when we need  help.
They too want their children to grow up a compasionate, intelligent and healthy
member of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless we can scientifically prove that excellence are born with a certain race, 
it doesn't make any sense to insist a person of a certain skin colour is
only eligable to run a certain public school. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to satisfy nonsense demands and requirements that do not
improve the education level of our children, our public education should 
refocus itself on what is universally important to the growth of a child into becoming 
a young adult capable of thinking for herself what is good for her own future, 
regardless of skin colour or faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The public shool focus is on education, and not just a tool to unite society&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at it another way: The current rheoteric that we're seeing basically also
says that part of the blame for our national disunity are on schools, but when in fact schools in
it's pure form should only be focusing on giving education to our children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subject of national unity is &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; our public schools and doesn't stop
there. Our 7-year old child starting her formal education doesn't care what skin
colour she is, or what colour her new friend that'll be sitting next to her in
class will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Disunity is not a problem that the schools started&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every child when born doesn't know what race or religion is. If they know that
they are &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; than other people and should only stick to their own kind by the time 
they get to primary school, then the problem of disunity has started even before
getting to the schools. How would we expect schools to solve a problem which it
did not start?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't make our public schools one of the scapegoats of our inability to get our
act together, and don't expect the schools to solve a problem it did not
start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Focusing on good education and it's resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve the level of education that we expect for our children requires us to
step back and reasses the ability of us to educate them the way we want them to
be. It is a fool's errand to say that we want the best, when we are only willing
or able to move forward at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having capable teachers, and teachers who can focus only on teaching without
being burdened with adminstrative tasks is a no-brainer and I know we are aware 
of the need to focus and fix these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other aspect that have not being discussed though is the fact that we're
spreading our resources thin due to political pressure based on racial or
religious identity instead of educational needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if a child wants to learn a particular language, why would she
need to go to a vernacular school to do so? Why shouldn't we give the
opportunity for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; our children to learn these different languages at any
school that they go to?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only obvious reason this is happening is that we don't
have enough capable teachers to go around all of our schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not make rational or scientific sense to say we need a totally different
school stream just to learn a language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of having teachers assigned to different schools all over the
country, we should have lesser amount of schools. The different languages, or
subjects that are being taught differently at vernacular schools should be
made avaialable and taught at all the schools that we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What works at the the better schools should be shared and emulated among other
schools, increasing the education level bar evenly across all our schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robin, one of the callers pointed out that vernacular schools strive because they do
offer something or maybe even do something better which are missing from the national schools.
We should figure this out, and emulate them on all our schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to have a single stream school, where everyone can learn all
these different languages with everyone else. We will have a single budget, and
a single focus on education, practicing best practices learned via a single way to run
all our schools, with less overhead burden due to the different wants or
political needs that has nothing to do with a good education. Our teaching resources will be
more focused on teaching rather than than be bogged down by non-educational matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the public education sphere, languages should be regarded as just
another tool to communicate and to educate our children, and are
just subjects to be learned instead of them being symbols of racial or religious
identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mixed signals: It's confusing and it's insane&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judging from the perspective that our general public is viewing our school
system, we're not doing very well. Most of us complain that our children are
being burdened by more and more things to learn, and at the same time they are
not getting to know one another any better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Year in and year out, we focus on the amount of &lt;em&gt;As&lt;/em&gt; that our children get, how
many did not get the scholarship that they want, how many couldn't speak good
English, and how they are getting more and more polarised day by day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the fact is in essence we're not changing the way we're teaching our
children. We think we give them education by adding all these new information
and subjects at school for them to pass exams, and we think we're giving them
"education", but are we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we read the news of children killing themselves because they did not get
the results that they wanted, we raise our hands and say what have we done? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we continue to demand As as if this is the only way forward and complain
when there is not enough places in the universities because tens of thousands of
other children also received more &lt;em&gt;As&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes for putting the schools as a scapegoat for our disunity. We say we want
our people to unite and be treated as one and as equals, but when we say all our
schools should be one and all our children learn under a single roof, we raise
our hands and shout and say that &lt;em&gt;we need to protect culture&lt;/em&gt; and it's &lt;em&gt;racism
and discrimination&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are just making our children confused by saying something and doing something
else. They will just grow up cynical and untrusting of the adults they see, and
worst, they will grow up &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; those exact same adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, sixty years down the road when we started of with our current formula of
education, have we achieved in terms of quality or strength among our society
that we wanted to achieve at that time? Just judging from what our society is
debating right now, it does not seem so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we expect different results now, but without changing the approach we have been
taking all this while, we are insane!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our multiculturalism does not die with the schools.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It dies when we only care about our own lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove all references to a particular language or race types of school, 
from vernacular schools, the Malay College to the MRSM schools by MARA&lt;sup id="fnref:footnote1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:footnote1" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
schools and make all these schools accessible without prejudice to any child of Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to play divisive politics and call out each other by their skin
colour, fine. But leave our children and &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; schools out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:Ref1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mytn50.com/?language=eng"&gt;TN50&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:Ref1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:footnote1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically &lt;strong&gt;Majlis Amanah Rakyat&lt;/strong&gt;, despite it's name, doesn't seem to consider non-bumiputras as &lt;em&gt;rakyat&lt;/em&gt; to be helped as it's mandate is focused only helping bumiputras&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:footnote1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="unity"></category><category term="schools"></category><category term="bfm"></category></entry><entry><title>エアアジアが在留カードの確認する件</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/why-does-airasia-check-zairyu-card-ja.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-11T12:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-03-11T12:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2017-03-11:en/why-does-airasia-check-zairyu-card-ja.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;エアアジアを搭乗する際に、在留カードの提示強引に求められたことがあったので、エアアジアに問い合わせをして
クレームを入れたときの背景やその回答をメモの代わりにここに書いておく。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;先日10周年の会社記念の社員旅行のため、エアアジアでオンラインで航空券を予約して、
出発日に羽田空港のカウンタでチェックインすると、パスポートと搭乗券の他、在留カードの提示も求められました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今までANAや他の航空会社を乗ったとき、パスポート以外に在留カードの提示求められたことがなかったし、
すべての外国の搭乗者は在留カード持っているわけがないからなぜ我々だけか、
あと在留カードの提示は公務を執行する官憲の者以外は基本的に求められることはないと思いますのでちょっと変だなーと思って
「必要ですか」と訊きました。
カウンタの職員の女性は「はい、必要です。中にまた入管に確認されるのでスムーズに搭乗できるように」
と言われました。私は、「そうしたら、ここで提示を拒否します。入管みたいな官憲の方に任せればいいじゃない。」
そうすると「上司に確認します」とカウンタの女性を言って、上司らしきの方と相談したあとに戻ってきたら
「義務です。提示しなかければ搭乗手続き進めません」と言い切って、仕方がなく提示をしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;その後やっぱり腑に落ちませんでした。予約時でも必要の書類として「在留カード」も掲載なかったし、意味もなく
「外国人だから在留資格や在留カードをチェックしよう」という行為自体は人種差別の行為ととらえることも無理もないので
エアアジアの&lt;a href="https://eform.airasia.com/"&gt;Eフォーム&lt;/a&gt;から問い合わせをしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;マレーシア国籍で日本中長期滞在の者ですが、マレーシア行きのフライトのチェックイン時にパスポートを提示したにも関わらず在留カードの提示が求められました。航空券を購入したときでも、サイト上でも「在留カードの提示が必要」ということどこでも掲載がなかったので、びっくりしました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;他の航空会社を利用した際にパスポート以外は在留カード等を求められたことがなかったので違和感を感じ、提示することを断ったのですが、御社のスタッフは「義務ですから」と言い、提示しなければフライト搭乗拒否すると言っています。そもそも、在留カードの提示を求めることできるのは、官憲の方だけで、航空会社のスタッフは強制的に求められることはないと思います。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本国籍の方ももちろん、短期滞在の外国の方（在留カード持ってないもの）がパスポートだけで十分サービス提供が行ってることにも関わらず、強制的に在留カード持ってるものだけ別扱いをすることはどうかと思います。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そこで、以下の質問を答えてください。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) 在留カード持参の者だけが在留カードを提示求められるのはなぜですか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) その理由は何かの法令または行政の指導基づいたことでしょうか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) 他航空会社を実施してないので御社だけが実施することになってるということなので自主的に行っていると思いますが、パスポートで十分のはずなのに提示を拒否した乗客に対してサービスを拒否することを問題と思います。これに対してどう思いますか？
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;そうすると、2週間後以下の回答がきました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;本件、お待たせしており大変申し訳ございません。
弊社にて調査した結果を以下のとおり回答させていただきます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) 在留カード持参の者だけが在留カードを提示求められるのはなぜですか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) その理由は何かの法令または行政の指導基づいたことでしょうか。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;弊社では在留カードをお持ちの外国籍のお客様でかつ日本発着のフライトのご予約をお持ちのお客様については、パスポートに加え、日本への再入国の要件をお客様が満たしているか確認するため、お持ちの在留カードを必ず確認させて頂いております。
なお、この対応は入国管理局の規定に基づいたものである旨申し添えます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;羽田空港の弊社地上業務担当部署によると、IQBAL様のご予約は羽田クアラルンプール間の往復のご予約でしたので、カウンターのスタッフが在留カードの提示をお願いさせて頂いたということです。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;==================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) 他航空会社を実施してないので御社だけが実施することになってるということなので自主的に行っていると思いますが、パスポートで十分のはずなのに提示を拒否した乗客に対してサービスを拒否することを問題と思います。これに対してどう思いますか？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;==================================================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;弊社では、入国管理局の規定に従い、日本発着のフライトのご予約をお持ちであり、かつ在留カードをお持ちの外国籍のお客様については在留カードを渡航書類の一部として取り扱っております。
そのため、在留カードをご提示頂けない場合、お客様が利用された羽田クアラルンプール間のフライトに適用される弊社の運送約款(7.1(i))に従い運送拒否をさせていただく場合もございます。
なお、弊社にて調査しましたところ、他の航空会社においても日本発着のフライトのご予約をお持ちであり、かつ在留カードをお持ちの外国籍のお客様に対しては在留カードの確認を行っております。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;しかしながら今回弊社地上係員の言動、また説明を十分に行わなかったことによりIQBAL様におかれましては大変ご不快な思いをさせてしまいましたことを心よりお詫び申し上げます。
今後更なるサービス向上に努めると共に、お客様に快適なご旅程をお送り頂けるよう社員一同一層気を引き締めて参ります。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ということだそうです。
個人的にはこれで納得できると思います。外国（アメリカやビサが必要の国に）へ行く時にチェックイン時にその国へ入国できる
資格を持っているかどうかをチェックされることが同じと考えています（ただそのときはパスポートだけをチェックされるけど）。
もちろん、片道のチケットだけをかっておいて日本に戻るかどうか本人が決まってないときに航空会社またわざわざ在留カード
をみることになったら意味合いが違っているけど。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;それにしてもエアアジア側として、事前説明が不十分だと思いますので、予約時や、チェックイン時に「往復のチケットをご購入の中長期滞在
の外国のお客様の再入国要件を確認するため在留カードを確認させていただいています」と一言を置いて貰えれば、誤解を招いた不愉快の
思いをさせることがないかなと思います。それを指摘すると、更にエアアジアから以下の回答を頂いています。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;この度は貴重なご意見を頂きましてありがとうございます。
IQBAL様より頂いたご意見は担当部署に申し伝え、今後のサービス向上に繋げさせて頂きます。
在留カードなど渡航書類を確認する際にはなぜ確認する必要があるのか、往復便をお持ちなので確認させて頂く必要がある、などといった明確な理由をもってお客様にご案内をするよう改善に努めます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;今後このようなことがないよう、社員一同気をつけて参りますので是非またエアアジアの翼をお選び頂きます様お願いを申し上げます。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;エアアジア　カスタマーケア&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本にまだ一般的にこの辺のことの意識は低いところがあると思いますので、皆さんと一緒に誰にでも（女性・マイノリティ・外国人含む）住みやすい日本にして良くしていきましょう。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;日本に戻る場所にしている限り私達の未来は一緒ですから。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="エアアジア"></category><category term="在留カード"></category><category term="外国人"></category></entry><entry><title>The Malaysia's brain drain dilemma</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/the-malaysian-brain-drain-dilemma.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-28T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-01-28T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2017-01-28:en/the-malaysian-brain-drain-dilemma.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the original article which was published on 28th Feb 2017 in The Malay Mail Online
titled &lt;a href="http://m.themalaymailonline.com/what-you-think/article/believing-in-malaysias-future-and-potential-iqbal-abdullah"&gt;Believing in Malaysia’s future and
potential&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://m.themalaymailonline.com/malaysia/article/the-other-side-of-malaysias-brain-drain-story"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; 
article concerning Malaysia's brain drain phenomena on The Malay Mail Online 
brought me thinking on this fine Saturday morning of the 1st day of the
New Lunar Year, and I want to write on what I think of the &lt;em&gt;Malaysian Brain Drain Dilemma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malaysia spends time, money and effort to attract Malaysian overseas to return
to Malaysia and contribute back to the country. The idea of getting people to
contribute to the development of the country is on the right track: Heck, it's
the only track that we have! There are absolutely no alternatives to &lt;em&gt;not
wanting people&lt;/em&gt; to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I do not see the point of getting &lt;em&gt;Malaysians to Malaysia&lt;/em&gt; in
order to achieve that. I feel the narrative of showing better lives for
Malaysians who returned home after years away, or of Malaysians who succeeded
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they left home is missing the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In the 21st century you can be anywhere and still contribute&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, improvements in infrastructure, information technology and travel makes
it possible for any of us to be anywhere on this planet. In a 8-hour period you
can be in Helsinki or if you spend 30 hours, you can be in Beunos Aires. You can
communicate via email, share information on websites and discuss ideas face-to
face via Hangouts or Facetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who want to contribute to something are passionate at what they do and 
will know that they want to contribute. The missing piece is the effort that we
spend to identify these people, reach out to them and connect them to like-minded
people or institutions that can help them amplify their contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TalentCorp says they have approved 4000 people within a period of 5 years since
2011. Malaysian overseas are estimated at 1 million people, which translates to
only 0.004%. Is 1000 per year of people enough to contribute? Is 0.004% an
acceptable acception rate after 5 years? Are we doing too little, or is this too much?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps TalentCorp's mandate is to identify and attract only talents with skills that
can only be utilized if they are present in the country, like surgeons to do
surgery. But we know contributing to something is more than that, and we need all the help
we can get, not only from the sciences but also engineering and arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also must not forget the home grown talents and people that are doing
wonderous jobs. Overseas Malaysias have different backgrounds, ideas and
approaches to the same problem we all have and these differences are what we
want to be accesible to our home grown talents. They can learn from each other,
improve and make something better together. Creating the missing piece of connecting
these dots between locals and abroad Malaysiams is where we should put more effort in,
regardless if the overseas talent will be coming home or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The writer checking email in front of Mont Saint Michel" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/montsaintmichel.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a picture of the writer checking his email taken in front of Mont Saint Michel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home is where the heart is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part is the most important factor of all: Where we call home. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home is not where we were born. Making a place home is a self-conscious
decision based on the different situation, personality and opportunities for any
given individual. This should and must be the overarching target for any 
returning program that we want to carry out: &lt;strong&gt;Making Malaysia home.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once someone calls a place home, the good and the bad will be taken in stride.
It is human nature to better their own home, for themselves and the generations
to come, and when we can get people who want to contribute calling Malaysia
their home, it will be a sustainable success story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although based on the article above, there are individuals who would return back
to Malaysia because they did not find the bed or roses they thought were waiting
for them whereever they were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Who cares if there’s corruption and crime in Malaysia? I just go back, make
heaps of money, then live in a condo with proper security. Solved. Whereas
here, I’m just an average Joe, and I’m struggling just to keep my head above
water".  - See more at:
&lt;a href="//m.themalaymailonline.com/malaysia/article/the-other-side-of-malaysias-brain-drain-story#sthash.Z6zLaSYD.dpuf"&gt;http://m.themalaymailonline.com/malaysia/article/the-other-side-of-malaysias-brain-drain-story#sthash.Z6zLaSYD.dpuf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These people do not call Malaysia their home. Making money is their intention,
and when there are better opportunities elsewhere, they move on. What we should
focus on for the long term are the stayers, the builders and the committed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this is what we agree to, to make Malaysia home, so the next big question is: 
&lt;em&gt;How do you convince people to call Malaysia their home?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, lets think of &lt;em&gt;what makes a good home?&lt;/em&gt;. Obviously you would not want to
live in a home that is fighting all the time. You do not want to live in a home
that is wrapped in poisonous polluting gasses. You &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to live in a home that
is peaceful, clean and conducise to health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should accept and understand that the universal values that attract human beings 
with a purpose applies and this is where we should concentrate our effort in: 
The values of justice, fairness, equality, fair reward for hard work, 
a genuine effort in betterment, a chance to better oneself, rule of law: 
Similar to the so-called &lt;strong&gt;The American Dream&lt;/strong&gt;, a slogan that made
America the place to be for all people having dreams of a better future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have an upperhand over overseas Malaysians to call Malaysia home, as they 
have family, roots and the eternal love for Malaysian food. But we should not take 
those for granted. There are more things that needs to be done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And then it's not only Malaysians&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's face it: Globalisation means people, capital and goods will move around at
a much easier and faster pace than it has ever before. Our competition is no
longer our neighbours like Singapore, Thailand or Indonesia, but it's New York,
Rio de Janeiro, Beirut, Paris or even Banjul. It's not countries anymore but cities: 
Cities now try to attract the best people from anywhere around the world to come and live there.
If people would not want to stay in Kuala Lumpur, all of these other cities will
woo them and are more than happy to welcome their wealth, expertise and passion.
The faster we realize this, the better it is for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point here is that when we get our head around at aiming to make Malaysia our
home, the universal values that apply to a good home will apply and attract many more
people, regardless of nationality, colour and creed. This is what makes a
country great: People believing in it and wanting to participate in it's growth
process. All these believers will come, and call Malaysia their home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when we reach this stage, we will be in a totally different playing field altogether. 
It will no longer be what race we are, or who are sons of soil, or where we are
from but we will be in the race to be the best in the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe in this vision of our country, where everyone wants to make it their
home, and believe in its potential and future. In the end, this is what we
mostly desire now: Believers in our country, it's potential and it's future.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="talents"></category><category term="humans"></category><category term="brain-drain"></category></entry><entry><title>Yang di-Pertuan Agong is not "king".</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/agong-and-not-king.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-12-05T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2016-12-05:en/agong-and-not-king.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was an email I sent to The Star on referring to the Malaysian Head of State
using the appropriate proper noun. It was not published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I refer to your news article on 16th Nov 2016 with the title
&lt;a href="http://www.thestar.com.my/news/nation/2016/11/16/king-and-queen-attend-parade-of-thanks-for-14th-yang-dipertuan-agong/"&gt;King and Queen attend parade of thanks for 14th Yang di-Pertuan
Agong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I read in your paper news about our Yang di-Pertuan Agong
and your paper refers to him as King and his consort as Queen, I
cringe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We Malaysians do not have a king. Spain has a king. Sweden has a king.
Monaco has a king. Japan has an emperor, while we Malaysian have our
Agong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a unique position even within this small world of ours. A king
generally implies a hereditary line of monarchs with power passed down
between families. Our Yang di-Pertuan Agong is elected and even has a
deputy which are not from the same family unlike kings which have
crown princes which are nearly the time sons of the same family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our passports also refers to the Agong as "His Majesty the Yang
di-Pertuan Agong of Malaysia".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agong is not a hereditary role, is a proper noun and referring to
a specific and important role in our country. There is no equivalent
english translation for our Agong, as the English language came from a
region and time where a ruler is a king and have absolute powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, you can refer to our Agong by addressing him by
"His Majesty" and his consort as "Her Majesty", or even the "Supreme
Commander of the Malaysian Armed Forces" if you'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the few English papers with wide circulation in the country,
we can assume that your good paper will be read by many foreigners
visiting our shores. It would be best to give the proper introduction
to them concerning our Yang di-Pertuan Agong, by correctly referring
to our unique elected Head of State lest they'l have the impression
that the Federation of Malaysia have "kings".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="agong"></category></entry><entry><title>Let's stop saying hello</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/no-greeting-condo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2016-11-09:en/no-greeting-condo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I saw this on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person wrote to the local newspaper telling the story of his condominium
making a new rule to not allow greeting each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the story goes, one of the parents were telling the management comittee 
that they were teaching their children to not greet anyone that they know, 
and since it's difficult for children to know a person who is an occupant of the
condo complex or not, the parent were asking the comittee to make a rule to not
allow greetings in the condo complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, one of the older occupants were also saying that since their
greetings always goes unaswered and doesn't make them feel any better, why not
we just stop with all the greetings altogether? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the occupants have reached an agreement not to greet each other, and now
they need to publish the new rule so that the rest of the condo complex
occupants know and follow it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="living together"></category><category term="greeting people"></category></entry><entry><title>あいさつをやめましょう。</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/../ja/no-greeting-condo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2016-11-09:en/../ja/no-greeting-condo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Twitterで以下の投稿を見かけたが、&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Letter to the editor on no greeting condo" src="http://iqbalabd.me/en/images/no-aisatsu-twitter.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;読んでビックリした。教育上だからと言って周りの社会まで巻き込んで近所の付き合い方（というか防犯対策上も問題になりそうだが）を根本的に変えちゃう
というのはどうかと思うけど。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;「マンション内のあいさつは禁止」&lt;/strong&gt; という張り紙でもだすのでしょうか。やっぱりこっちも理解苦しんでいるわ。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="近所付き合い"></category><category term="マンション生活"></category><category term="あいさつ"></category></entry><entry><title>Can Entrepreneurship Be Taught?</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/can-entrepreneurship-be-taught.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-12T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-03-12T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2015-03-12:en/can-entrepreneurship-be-taught.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mymagic.my/about/"&gt;MaGIC&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="https://cherylyeoh.com/"&gt;Cheryl Yeoh&lt;/a&gt; 
gave her views on if entrepreneurship can be taught in &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1FbbK89"&gt;The Star, March 3
2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to add my comments, based on my different experiences and
motivation from the context of teaching entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My views on entrepreneurship are purely based on experience. I did not have any
formal education on entrepreneurship, (I am trained as an engineer) nor my
immediate family members have been examples of entrepreneurship. As it is now,
out my siblings and my parents, only I are currently earning a living from a
business that I run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these experiences of mine, I believe that entrepreneurship are not
dissimilar to fado, the traditional music of Lisbon. You can nuture the feel for
fado (having many fado houses and public performances, as well as exposure from
the media), you can learn how to write and perform fado (by watching and
learning from the great fado maestros on how they perform their art) but alas
you cannot teach fado. There will be pointers on techniques which you can pass
on, but it is impossible for you to teach "how to fado". This sentiment is
echoed by all the great fado players, and I am very sure it is the same for any
art form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to an interesting take on entrepreneurship that I believe in:
That it is a mix of science and art form. It is science from the way that you
measure success: Because it is a business, you can measure what is the profit
margin, or the earnings per stock, or valuation or market capitalization. Based
on this numbers, so called investor will tell you if a business is growing,
stagnating or losing ground and if you should invest in a certain business. The
more these numbers show a positive trend, the better it is for the business&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do you get to that measurable success is, at the very best, not
measurable. Best practices from a certain market, when brought over might not
work the same way in a different market. The best we have the franchise types
turn key model which implements best practices but by different people, but even
that still doesn't work the same all the time everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful entrepreneurship requires more than understanding the numbers and
theories like what we learn in a business school sitting for an MBA. Business
and entrepreneurship are two different animals: A successful entrepreneur can
create a successful business, but a successful business might not create the
successful entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that context I very much agree with what Cheryl has pointed out: That the
Stanford Technology Ventures Program (STVP) does not look at purely the numbers
of startup companies created. A performance indicator to gauge if
entrepreneurship is taking hold that is based the amount of companies created is
nonsensical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't make sense and it doesn't show anything other than, well, the amount
of companies created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A top-down approach stating a target of so and so amount of companies should be
created to boost entrepreneurship, which I have noticed we, from time and time
again prefer to do, will only lead to more insubstantial companies and nonsense
capital distribution, with very little impact on creating resilient and
successful entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, a much more pedal-to-steel indicator that directly connects to the
would-be entrepreneurs will serve this purpose better. We can learn from
Stanford on how they use the amount of students who oversubscribe to their
courses or the ratings the students have given. Entrepreneurship is a career
path; For me personally, it is a way to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should treat entrepreneurship like any other career path. Students from young
should know that being an entrepreneur is also a viable career, like being a
policewoman, a mechanic, a pilot, or a lawyer or a doctor. But unlike a
policewoman who enforces the law or a pilot who flies a plane, the entrepreneur
creates value to the public and her customers by solving problems with a purpose
that will be sustainable for her, her family and her employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the end, it is up to the entrepreneur on why she decides to become one.
For the pilot, it might be the blue skies and travelling the world. For the
policewoman, it might be because of her sense of justice and conviction. This
reason or purpose, in the end, is the single most important driver behind
successful entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing wanting to achieve this goal and being able to do so by creating
sustainable value is the first step of being an entrepreneur. Unfortunately this
cannot be taught. What we, as the society and the education system can the best
do is to say that these goals can be achieved and have tangible tools like
infrastructure and access to human and monetary capital accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any good artist, give them the tools, step back and watch them work! &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ktmb"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="entrepreneurship"></category></entry><entry><title>So you're CEO</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/so-you-are-ceo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-21T10:20:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-10-21T10:20:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2012-10-21:en/so-you-are-ceo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On my flight on Singapore Airlines from Changi to KLIA I read an interesting
interview of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tan_Suee_Chieh"&gt;Tan Suee Chieh&lt;/a&gt; in The Straits Times Opinion section (Fri Oct 19
2012 edition).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that interview Tan basically talks about going "from well to good", and how
this is a departure from how he usually did things before going on board as head
of Singapore's NTUC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this excerpt of the interview particularly interesting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I worked in commercial companies for 25 years. My job as CEO of a listed
company has always been to maximise profits. And my obligation is to give as
little as possible to the customer, subject to market share and profit
considerations. But my job at NTUC Income is to give as much as possible to the
policyholders as a group. It's two different mindsets."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as an outifit out to make a profit everything is subject to profit
considerations. But I feel that being CEO or the leader even for an unlisted, 
3 person family business, with obligations to &lt;em&gt;give as little as possible to the
customer&lt;/em&gt; while in the same stride talking about &lt;em&gt;maximising profits&lt;/em&gt; is
misguided at best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how our Asian CEOs on this part of the world generally think what their
mandate is all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my role as a leader, in a nutshell my work boils down to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give good returns to shareholders by maximizing profits, as they are the ones taking the risk to put up the money for the business in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand in the customer's shoes and give them as much as possible making them happy, which will get you more money to do point 1 above. You are where you are because your customers are. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empower your employees and then stand out of their way so that they can please your customer which will lead to point 2 above and consequently to point 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should not be (and it never is) a zero sum game. Maximising profits does not
mean giving as little as possible to your customer.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="asian business"></category><category term="leadership"></category></entry><entry><title>KTMB should follow right train of thought</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/ktmb-should-follow-right-train-of-thought.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-12-25T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2009-12-25T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2009-12-25:en/ktmb-should-follow-right-train-of-thought.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was an &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/TxHZCy"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; I sent to The Star on Christmas Day 2009 about how terrible
KTMB Komuter service was. I was pretty pissed at that time. I don't understand
how KTMB cannot understand this very simple thing on providing a decent service to
it's customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I sent the email, I got a call from The Star while I was in Jaya Jusco in
Malacca and the person wanted to confirm that what I wrote about KTMB's aim of
getting MYR1 profit was correct before they published it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ON DEC 12, I took KTM’s Ekspres Sinaran Pagi from KL Sentral bound for
Singapore, which was originally scheduled to depart at 8.30am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I waited at the terminal, the departure time was rescheduled to 8.40am
and again to 8.55am. The train finally departed at 9am, and we reached
Singapore one hour later than the scheduled time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the KTM Komuter from Mid Valley to Seremban (Rawang-Seremban route) on
Dec 22, we waited from 9.10pm and the train arrived only at 9.40pm. We
finally reached Seremban at around 11pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KTMB customers waiting at the Mid Valley station resigned themselves to the
waiting, and some even opened up their work on the cement floor and tried to
get something done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electronic signs at the platform were confusing and did not show correct
information. We were not notified the reason for the delays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain passengers were inconsiderate, refusing to allow passengers to alight
first before boarding, pushing ahead with their big backpacks, having their
handphone ringtones on full volume and refusing to give up their seats for a
blind mother and child who boarded in Serdang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of taking the Komuter from Mid Valley to Seremban has left me
tired. I felt I have grown older by 10 years and my will to live has gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two points that I wish to share with KTMB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s economy, KTMB must realise that it is not an operator of
      railways. It must realise that it is a service provider, not much different
      from taxis or retail outlets. It just so happens that the service provider
      called KTMB is providing its service through railways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money is in transporting people, not goods. If KTMB truly wishes to
   reach its stated target of even RM1 profit, stay there or even go beyond
   that, it has to understand that the service of transporting people, in a
   timely and comfortable manner, will be the single most important revenue
   provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are important concepts that everyone in KTMB must realise and
understand, from the CEO down to the person maintaining the ticket machines
at the stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a layman’s point of view KTMB has great potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With highways being built every day and airline flights getting cheaper, it
is more important than ever that KTMB realise its potential as a service
provider, and the strength that its assets hold. KTMB owns tracks and
stations which are not affected by traffic yet that go direct to the heart of
towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malaysia will change like other developed nations, where more and more people
commute to work from out-of-state into Kuala Lumpur. We see this happening
right here and now, and it is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are too many cars on the roads and everyone is tired of traffic jams in
the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is in place that will allow KTMB to be the leading transportation
service provider. All that KTMB needs to do is to leverage these assets and
by being reliable and punctual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be reliable and on time do not require KTMB to change its rolling stock
immediately, nor does it require it to send its staff to Tokyo to study how
JR (Japan Railways Group) does its job. All KTMB has to do is ride its own
trains and make notes of what it’s doing right and what it’s doing wrong, and
then fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IQBAL ABDULLAH, 
Petaling Jaya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="ktmb"></category><category term="current affairs"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="public transportation"></category><category term="trains"></category></entry><entry><title>Meritokrasi ubat pahit tetapi mujarab</title><link href="http://iqbalabd.me/en/meritokrasi-ubat-pahit-ms.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</published><updated>2010-10-04T18:40:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:iqbalabd.me,2001-08-09:en/meritokrasi-ubat-pahit-ms.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an opinion letter I wrote when I was staying in Higashi-Kawaguchi, fresh
out of college during the summer of my first job at Sun Microsystems. It was published in 
&lt;a href="http://ww1.utusan.com.my/utusan/info.asp?y=2001&amp;amp;dt=0809&amp;amp;pub=Utusan_Malaysia&amp;amp;sec=Rencana&amp;amp;pg=re_06.htm"&gt;Utusan Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;
on 9th August 2001:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saya percaya dengan tahap teknologi dan capaian media kita sekarang, seseorang
itu tidak perlu lagi lulus universiti untuk mendapatkan kebolehan baik di dalam
bidang tertentu, terutamanya sains maklumat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetapi pokoknya ia bukan sahaja mengenai minat atau kebolehan, tetapi mentaliti
dan disiplin pelajar Melayu kita. Oleh sebab untuk membaiki mentaliti dan
disiplin pelajar Melayu ini juga, maka Perdana Menteri, Datuk Seri Dr. Mahathir
mencadangkan pelaksanaan sistem meritokrasi (walaupun sebagai eksperimen) mulai
sesi pengambilan pelajar akan datang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setelah melalui kehidupan belajar di universiti (walaupun saya belajar di salah
sebuah universiti awam di Jepun), saya dapat memahami jika dikatakan, walaupun
kelulusan yang baik itu penting, tetapi sebenarnya pembelajaran di univerisiti
adalah lebih daripada itu. Jika dibandingkan dengan kursus-kursus lain, kita
sedia maklum memang pembelajaran di universiti lebih susah dan membebankan,
kerana salah satu sebabnya ialah terdapat subjek-subjek lain yang langsung tiada
kaitan dengan kursus seseorang itu, tetapi ia harus diambil bagi memenuhi syarat
kreditnya untuk menamatkan kursus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetapi tidakkah kita terfikir, jika sistem pendidikan kita mahu menghasilkan
seorang programmer atau seorang jurutera, mengapa tidak dari awal lagi gaya
pembelajaran di univerisiti diubah? Ini kerana institut universiti itu bukan
hanya mahu menghasilkan seorang programmer atau jurutera tetapi seorang
profesional semua bidang, yang berdisiplin dan berwibawa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidak ada gunanya jika seseorang itu boleh menulis kod program yang cukup bagus
tetapi masih tidak memahami sejarah negaranya, oleh itu tiada sikap patriotik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bertahan selama empat tahun di universiti dan berhadapan dengan segala macam
masalah, kebanyakan bergantung dari dalam diri sendiri dan selebihnya dari luar,
telah mengajar saya pelbagai perkara. Bukan tidak pernah semasa di universiti,
saya menangis seorang diri di belakang dewan kuliah kerana rasa terlalu tertekan
untuk mendapatkan gred bagus dalam satu subjek yang saya langsung tidak
mempunyai minat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bukan tidak pernah dalam empat tahun itu saya terfikir untuk berhenti sahaja
belajar di universiti kerana saya rasa minat saya tidak ada dalam bidang
tertentu, dan saya percaya kebolehan diri untuk melakukan apa yang saya minat.
Pernah semasa saya di tahun dua, saya berdiri di hadapan pensyarah selama lebih
dua jam, sambil diherdik dan dimarahi kerana tugasan saya yang dikatakannya
tidak berapa elok walaupun saya bersengkang mata lebih tiga hari tiga malam
untuk menyiapkannya. Pada masa itu hanya Tuhan sahaja yang tahu betapa sakitnya
hati saya dan betapa mahu saya pulang saja ke Malaysia kerana tidak tahan lagi
dengan satu sistem pembelajaran yang apa-kenapa-dan-bagaimananya langsung
tidak saya fahami.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semasa saya di tahun empat, pernah saya diminta oleh pensyarah untuk melakukan
pembentangan mengenai kajian yang sedang saya lakukan. Setelah membuat
pembentangan tersebut, saya telah dimarahi kerana pembentangan saya itu tidak
berapa memuaskan. Pensyarah tersebut berkata, Kenapa kamu tidak lakukan
seperti saya, dengan membuat nota dan rajah yang teliti, seperti saya lakukan
setiap kali kuliah? Saya berkata oleh kerana profesor adalah seorang
profesional dalam bidang tersebut, maka perkara itu sudah menjadi satu benda
yang biasa, dan tidak pula bagi saya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetapi beliau kemudian menjawab, Habis, kenapa kamu hadir di univerisiti?
Bukankah untuk menjadi seorang profesional? Saya terdiam. Memang benar kata
pensyarah saya itu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setelah memasuki alam pekerjaan, saya dapati sebenarnya apa yang diutamakan oleh
orang Jepun di sini bukanlah kelulusan peperiksaan ataupun kemahiran (walaupun
ia penting) tetapi kendiri dan sikap seseorang itu terhadap pekerjaannya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerana belajar itu suatu perkara yang tidak akan habis sehinggalah kita mati,
maka kemahiran dan pengetahuan masih boleh kita timba walaupun setelah tamat
universiti. Tetapi sikap itu harus dipupuk dari muda, bak kata pepatah,
Meluntur buluh biar dari rebungnya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empat tahun di universiti mengajar kita untuk bersikap profesional, berdisiplin
untuk mengikut sistem, tidak anti-establishment, sabar, gigih, bersemangat dan
bercita-cita tinggi. Apa yang tersurat di atas segulung ijazah itu tidak dapat
menggambarkan seribu satu perkara yang tersirat. Tetapi malangnya jika dilihat
fenomena pelajar Melayu kita di universiti sekarang, mereka seperti hilang punca
tentang mengapa mereka di sana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mungkin pelajar Melayu kita, seperti juga remaja Jepun sekarang, yang terlalu
mewah atas titik peluh generasi sebelumnya, tidak faham akan apa itu erti
kesusahan, lantas hilang fokus dan lupa akan matlamat diri sebagai pemuda-pemudi
bangsa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jika seperti selalu, jalan keluar yang senang dan cepat diberikan, sehingga
kiamat pun, orang Melayu kita akan tetap mencari jalan mudah untuk keluar
daripada segala macam masalah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidak semua orang boleh menjadi genius kerana itu adalah anugerah Tuhan, tetapi
semua orang boleh bersikap profesional dan berdisiplin, kerana sikap itu boleh
dipupuk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kita harus mempunyai keyakinan terhadap pemuda-pemudi Melayu kita yang walaupun
tanpa bantuan kerajaan, masih boleh menunjukkan kelayakan cukup bagus sehingga
boleh memberi persaingan kepada kaum-kaum lain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lebih baik sistem meritokrasi ini dilaksanakan dalam keadaan kita berkuasa dan
boleh mengubahnya semula kepada sistem kuota jika ia tidak mencapai matlamat,
daripada ia dilakukan pada masa kita tiada kuasa dan tidak berkuasa untuk
memperbetulkan keadaan. Pelaksanaan sistem meritokrasi ini, walaupun ia pedih
dan pahit, tetapi saya percaya ia akan memberi ubat yang paling mujarab bagi
pewaris bangsa dan negara kita. Tabik saya kepada bakal mahasiswa Melayu yang
sanggup menerima cabaran ini. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IQBAL ABDULLAH, Kawaguchi, Jepun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="meritokrasi"></category><category term="hal ehwal semasa"></category><category term="malaysia"></category><category term="universiti"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="pembelajaran"></category></entry></feed>